Finding Aid for the J. Paul Getty Family Collected Papers, circa 1880s-1989, undated IA20009
Institutional Records and Archives
J. Paul Getty family collected papers
1880s-1989
undated
(bulk 1911-1977)
Institutional Records and Archives
Gaston, Teddy Getty, 1913-
Getty, Sarah C. (Sarah Catherine)
Bramlett, Norris (Cagle Norris)
Hewins, Ralph
Getty, J. Paul (Jean Paul), 1892-1976
Le Vane, Ethel
Getty, George F. (George Franklin), 1855-1930
IA20009
21 Linear Feet (30 boxes, 1 flat file)
The collection comprises collected materials related to art collector and oil tycoon J. Paul Getty and his parents, George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty. The collected papers on J. Paul Getty include some of his personal and business correspondence and other documents, dating from 1909 to 1976, providing insight into his art collecting activities, his business concerns, and his personal and family relationships. The materials also contain documents postdating Mr. Getty's death (1977, 1980-1989) that concern the management of his estate and eulogize his life and accomplishments. The George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty papers, dating from 1890 to 1939, primarily comprise family and oil business correspondence and offer researchers a glimpse into the Getty household. The collection includes correspondence, art and furniture inventories, financial records, legal documents, publications, ephemera, and photographs, dating from around the 1880s to 1989.
Acquisition Information
This collection was assembled from a number of sources and is comprised of the following accessions:
1986.IA.22 transferred by the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities
1986.IA.40 transferred by the J. Paul Getty Trust
1986.IA.48 transferred by the J. Paul Getty Museum (the material was originally part of accession no. 1986.IA.01 and was assigned no. 1986.IA.48 in January 2006 for purposes of providing better administrative control)
1987.IA.05 (unidentified source)
1987.IA.11 transferred by the J. Paul Getty Museum
1987.IA.16 transferred by the J. Paul Getty Estate
1992.IA.03 donated by Zeki Yonet
1997.IA.08 donated by unidentified dealer
1998.IA.07 donated by or acquired from Spencer A. Samuels & Co.
2002.IA.02 (unidentified source)
2004.IA.17 donated to the Institutional Archives by the Nethercutt Collection
2006.IA.05 transferred by the J. Paul Getty Trust
2007.IA.32 donated by Lynda Jenner
2009.IA.36 discovered by Getty Institutional Archives staff during review of unaccessioned legacy records
2010.IA.17 acquired from Scott J. Winslow Associates, Inc.
2011.IA.44 transferred by the J. Paul Getty Trust
2012.IA.37 transferred by the Getty Research Institute
2014.IA.02 donated by Scott J. Winslow
2018.IA.58 donated by John M. McDivitt
2019.IA.56 purchased from Bonhams
Restrictions on Access
The records described in accessions 1986.IA.22; 1986.IA.40; 1987.IA.05; 1987.IA.11; 1987.IA.16; 1992.IA.03; 1997.IA.08; 1998.IA.07; 2002.IA.02; 2004.IA.17; 2006.IA.05; 2007.IA.32; 2009.IA.36; 2012.IA.37; 2014.IA.02; 2018.IA.58; and 2019.IA.56 are available for use by qualified researchers.
Please note: materials that have been marked restricted or confidential must be removed from boxes prior to access.
With the exception of materials that have been marked restricted or confidential, the records described in accessions 1986.IA.48 and 2010.IA.17 are available for use by qualified researchers.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection comprises materials gathered from a variety of sources that relate to art collector and oil tycoon J. Paul Getty and his parents, George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty. The collection includes correspondence, art and furniture inventories, financial records, legal documents, publications, ephemera, and photographs, dating from approximately 1880 to 1989 and undated.
The collected papers on J. Paul Getty include some of his personal and business correspondence and other documents, providing insight into his art collecting activities, his business ventures, and his personal and family relationships. The financial records primarily describe the affairs of Getty family businesses as well as Getty's estate at the time of his death. The legal documents describe legal and financial relationships within the Getty family through correspondence, wills, prenuptial agreements, divorce decrees, financial settlements, child and spousal support agreements, and other supporting documents. The little material relating to his marriages is mostly represented among his legal files. Materials related to Mr. Getty's publications contain correspondence with co-authors and publishers, typescripts and drafts of his books, and copies of his published books and articles. The collected papers also contain documents postdating Mr. Getty's death (1977, 1980-1989) that concern the management of his estate and eulogize his life and accomplishments.
The collected George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty papers include letters, telegrams, hand-drawn maps, cancelled stock certificates, contracts, promissory notes, travel documents, receipts, and various forms of ephemera. The family correspondence includes letters written by J. Paul Getty to his parents that provide insight into the personal and early business relationships between George, Sarah, and Paul. While the family correspondence hints at the atmosphere of the Getty household, George's papers shed light on his early oil operations, including scouting potential drilling sites, day-to-day management of drilling activities, and his political efforts to protect his interests/land in the Osage Nation (part of the Indian Territory that was annexed by the United States government that later became the state of Oklahoma). Sarah's mostly peripheral involvement in the family business is evidenced by her correspondence with George and several notarized documents.
The photographs consist primarily of black-and-white photographs and negatives, dating from approximately the 1880s to the 1970s, of J. Paul Getty, family, friends, properties, and city and landscape views. The photographs also include several images of the J. Paul Getty Museum and galleries during its early years. The images are of various sizes, and are largely undated and unidentified. The majority of these photographs once belonged to J. Paul Getty, while a smaller number of them seem to have belonged to his father, George F. Getty I. The photographs come from several different sources, including Ralph Hewins, Getty's biographer.
Arrangement
These records are organized into three series:
Series I. J. Paul Getty papers, 1909-1977, 1982-1984, 1989, undated (bulk 1912-1976)
Series II. George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty papers, 1890, 1904-1921, 1928, 1931-1934, 1939, undated (bulk 1911-1912)
Series III. Photographs, 1880s-1970s, undated.
Biographical Note
American oil tycoon and art collector Jean Paul Getty was born in Minneapolis, Minnesota on December 15, 1892 to George Franklin Getty (1855-1930) and Sarah Catherine McPherson Risher Getty (1852-1941). George was an attorney and insurance executive whose 1903 visit to oil-rich Osage land in Indian Territory (a region that was annexed by the United States government that later became the State of Oklahoma in 1907) inspired him to lease land and begin drilling, launching his career in the petroleum industry. In 1905 the Getty family moved to Los Angeles, but George maintained his oil business in Oklahoma, traveling to the oil fields periodically. Jean Paul, called "Paul," attended a private military school before going on to college. He first attended the University of Southern California in Los Angeles and later transferred to the University of California, Berkeley (1909 to 1911). In November of 1912 he began his studies at Magdalen College at Oxford University in England and received a diploma in Politics and Economics in June 1913. He then enhanced his education by means of a Grand Tour of Europe, viewing art collections and ancient ruins that sparked his interest in art and antiquities. He also toured parts of the Middle East and North Africa before returning to the United States in September of 1914.
In 1914, Paul joined the family petroleum business and spent a year in the oil fields of Oklahoma. An investment in 160 acres near Stone Bluff, Oklahoma led to Paul's announcement two years later that he had earned his first million dollars. He then lived the carefree life of a rich young bachelor in Los Angeles for more than a year before his father convinced him to return to the oil business in Oklahoma. Soon thereafter Paul persuaded his father to shift the focus of the family business operations to the Los Angeles basin. Paul continued to work for the family company in addition to conducting oil drilling of his own, securing the family fortune by the time the stock market crashed in 1929. Upon his death in 1930, George left controlling interest in the company to Sarah. In 1934 Paul forced Sarah out of control of the company and gave her an annuity. His fortune grew as he acquired the controlling interest in several companies and became the head of a vast organization with activities in oil exploration, transportation, production and marketing, as well as minerals, manufacturing, real estate and agriculture. In the mid-1940s Paul bought the Saudi Arabian portion of the lease on the mineral rights in the Neutral Zone between Saudi Arabia and Kuwait; his wealth dramatically increased when this site produced oil in 1953.
Beginning in the early 1930s, J. Paul Getty lived in a house he built next to William Randolph Hearst's on the beach in Santa Monica. During World War II he moved to Tulsa, Oklahoma for four years to supervise wartime production of parts for Allied aircraft at his Spartan Aircraft plant. In 1945 he purchased 64 acres in Malibu, California and renovated the existing hacienda, known as the Ranch House, where he lived until 1951. (See finding aid IA20021 for records regarding the Ranch House.) When Getty departed the United States for Europe in 1951, he kept his Malibu estate for the display of his art collection and for his eventual return to California. The J. Paul Getty Museum Trust was incorporated in December 1953; The J. Paul Getty Museum at the Ranch House opened to the public in April 1954.
Getty had been collecting art since the 1930s. In 1938 he made his first major purchases: a group of furniture; a carpet that had belonged to Louis XIV, often called the "Ardabil Carpet"; and Rembrandt's Marten Looten (he donated the Ardabil Carpet and the Rembrandt to the Los Angeles County Museum of Art in 1954). Another of his strong interests was antiquities, inspired by his travels throughout Europe and by visits to the Vatican Museums. He took pride in being knowledgeable in the areas in which he was collecting and in finding bargains. Getty continued to collect art throughout his lifetime, despite occasional assertions that he was no longer in the market. While some objects were expressly purchased for the Getty Museum, Mr. Getty also maintained a personal art collection, some of which was on long-term loan to the museum. By 1968 his art collection had begun to outgrow the Ranch House and he began planning a new building on the property to properly house these works. He chose to pattern this new museum building after a first-century Roman country house, based primarily on the plans of the ancient Villa dei Papiri near Herculaneum. This museum, often called the Getty Villa, opened to the public on January 16, 1974.
After leaving the United States in 1951, Getty lived in hotel suites in Europe until 1960 when he moved to Sutton Place, a historic 72-room Tudor manor located 25 miles southwest of London. In 1957 Fortune magazine designated Getty as the world's wealthiest man, and he became the object of considerable public interest. For the rest of his life, both the respectable press and the tabloids reported on his perceived eccentricities and his private life.
Getty married and divorced five times and had five children with four of his wives.
First wife: Jeanette Demond, mother of George F. Getty II
Second wife: Allene Ashby
Third wife: Adolphine "Fini" Helmle, mother of Jean Ronald Getty
Fourth wife: Helen "Ann" Rork (also known as Helen Ann Rork Wilson and Helen Ann Rork Light), mother of Eugene Paul and Gordon Peter Getty
Fifth wife: Louise Dudley Lynch (also known as Theodora Lynch, Teddy Lynch, and Teddy Getty Gaston), mother of Timothy Ware Getty
J. Paul Getty died in England on June 6, 1976 without ever returning to California. Although he never saw the museum, he is buried at the Getty Villa property on a bluff overlooking the Pacific Ocean. Much to everyone's surprise, Getty left the bulk of his fortune to the museum, requesting that the funds be employed to promote "the diffusion of artistic and general knowledge."
J. Paul Getty's publications include:
Getty, J. Paul. The history of the oil business of George F. and J. Paul Getty from 1903 to 1939. Los Angeles (?), 1941.
Getty, J. Paul. Europe in the eighteenth century. [Santa Monica, Calif.]: privately printed, 1949.
Le Vane, Ethel, and J. Paul Getty. Collector's choice: the chronicle of an artistic odyssey through Europe. London: W.H. Allen, 1955.
Getty, J. Paul. My life and fortunes. New York: Duell, Sloan & Pearce, 1963.
Getty, J. Paul. The joys of collecting. New York: Hawthorn Books, 1965.
Getty, J. Paul. How to be rich. Chicago: Playboy Press, 1965.
Getty, J. Paul. The golden age. New York: Trident Press, 1968.
Getty, J. Paul. How to be a successful executive. Chicago: Playboy Press, 1971.
Getty, J. Paul. As I see it: the autobiography of J. Paul Getty. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1976.
Related Archival Materials Note
The following archival materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the people, programs, and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Institutional Archives
J. Paul Getty and the Ashby Sisters Papers, 1926-1992, undated. The Getty Research Institute (IA20013).
J. Paul Getty Diaries, 1938-1946, 1948-1976. The Getty Research Institute (IA40009).
Ralph Hewins Collected Papers for Biography of J. Paul Getty, 1957-1973, 1984 and undated. The Getty Research Institute (IA20012).
Bibliography
Information in the biographical note on J. Paul Getty was gleaned from the collection and from the following publications:
Getty, J. Paul. As I see it: the autobiography of J. Paul Getty. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1976.
Hewins, Ralph. The richest American: J. Paul Getty. New York: Dutton, 1960.
Oil fields -- Oklahoma -- Osage Reservation; Photographs; Ledgers (account books); Reports; Financial records; Legal documents; Publications; Art objects -- Collectors and collecting; Art museums; Billionaires -- United States -- 20th century; Entrepreneurship -- 20th century; Petroleum -- History -- United States -- 20th century; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Getty, Sarah C. (Sarah Catherine); Minnehoma Oil and Gas Company; Ada Oil Corporation; Getty, George F. (George Franklin), 1855-1930; San Joaquin Oil Company; Getty Oil Company; Oklahoma Oil Corporation; George F. Getty, Incorporated; J. Paul Getty Museum; Getty, J. Paul (Jean Paul), 1892-1976
- J. Paul Getty papers, 1909-1977; 1982-1984,; 1989,; undated; (bulk 1912-1976); Series I.; 17.6 Linear Feet (22 boxes, 1 flat file)
  Scope and Contents
  The collected papers on J. Paul Getty include some of his personal and business correspondence, records, and ephemera dating from 1909 to 1976, and provide insight into his art collecting activities, his business concerns, and his personal and family relationships. The collected papers also contain documents postdating Mr. Getty's death (1977, 1980-1989) that concern the management of his estate and eulogize his life and accomplishments.
  Material related to Mr. Getty's art collecting and collections include correspondence, inventories, photographs, invoices, reports, import/export documents, curators' notes, and clippings. The materials provide information on purchases, shipping, and insurance of works of art. The correspondence primarily comprises letters received by J. Paul Getty, the earliest correspondence being the most personal. The financial records primarily describe the financial well-being of Getty family businesses as well as Getty's estate at the time of his death. The legal documents describe legal and financial relationships within the Getty family through correspondence, wills, prenuptial agreements, divorce decrees, financial settlements, child and spousal support agreements, and other legal documents. Materials related to Mr. Getty's publications contain correspondence with co-authors and publishers, typescripts and drafts of his books, and copies of his published books and articles. The collected papers also contain various dissociated papers of J. Paul Getty related to his life and interests, including scattered diary entries.
  Please note that the Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute holds Mr. Getty's more complete diaries: J. Paul Getty Diaries (1938-1946, 1948-1976), Finding aid no. IA40009.
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged into four subseries:
  Series I.A. Art collecting and collections, 1934-1974, 1977, 1982, undated (bulk 1934-1974)
  Series I.B. Business and personal papers, 1909-1914, 1920-1977, undated
  Series I.C. Publications, typescripts, and related material, 1940-1976, 1989, undated (bulk 1940-1967)
  Series I.D. Ephemera and clippings, 1914-1920, 1932-1954, 1974, 1982-1984, undated.
  - Art collecting and collections, 1934-1974; 1977,; 1982,; undated; (bulk 1934-1974); Series I.A.; 2.4 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
    Material is arranged by type of material, beginning with correspondence, which is followed by inventories, curators' notes, and insurance policies.
    Material includes correspondence, inventories, photographs, invoices, reports, import/export documents, curators' notes, and clippings regarding J. Paul Getty's art collections and art collecting activities, dating 1934 to 1974, 1977, 1982, and undated. The records provide information on purchases, shipping, and insurance of works of art. Correspondence with art dealers comprises the bulk of the material. The inventories primarily concern Getty's art collection at Sutton Place, his estate in England. The Sutton Place tapestry inventory includes clippings about the estate after Getty's death. The curators' notes are diary excerpts and notes taken by Getty Museum curators who were given a brief opportunity to examine Mr. Getty's diaries after his death. The notes relate to the curators' areas of interest, such as the provenance and acquisition of art objects and the collecting habits of Mr. Getty; the notes do not reflect the contents of the diaries as a whole.
    - Art collections correspondence, 1934-1959; 1970-1972
      Material is arranged alphabetically by the surname or corporate name of the correspondent.
      - B miscellaneous, 1939-1954 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 1)
      - William L. Bane and Co., 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 2)
      - Mario Bellini, 1953-1954 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 3)
      - Benardout and Benardout, London, 1938-1943; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 4)
      - J.M. Botibol, 1939-1940; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 5)
      - Brill and Brill, Croydon Galleries, 1937-1942; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 6)
      - Gerald L. Brockhurst, 1938-1946 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 7)
      - C miscellaneous, 1937-1952 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 8)
      - Camerons, 1949-1951 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 9)
      - Christie, Manson and Woods, Ltd., 1938-1950 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 10, Box Shared 1987.IA.16-01; 2004.IA.17; 2009.IA.36; 2011.IA.44; 2022.IA.88)
      - T. Crowther and Son, 1937-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 11)
      - D miscellaneous, 1938-1941 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 12)
      - Duveen Brothers, Inc., 1939-1951; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 13-16)
      - F miscellaneous, 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 17)
      - Augustus Frank, 1934-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 18)
      - French and Company Inc., 1937-1941; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-01, Folder 19-22)
      - French and Company Inc., 1942-1959; 1970-1972; (7 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 1-7)
      - French and Company Loan, 1958 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 8)
      - Furnishings: correspondence regarding works of art, antiques, furniture, carpets and other furnishings for Mr. Getty's home, 1934-1945 (Box Shared 1987.IA.16-01; 2004.IA.17; 2009.IA.36; 2011.IA.44; 2022.IA.88)
      - G miscellaneous, 1938-1939; 1950 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 9)
      - Gill and Reigate, 1938 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 10)
      - Grosvenor Galleries, 1937-1938 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 11)
      - H miscellaneous, 1939; 1950 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 12)
      - Henry John Hatfield and Sons, Ltd., 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 13)
      - Hudson Forwarding and Shipping Co., Inc., 1938-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 14)
      - Hyde (John Alden Lloyd) through Knudson (Arvid O.), 1948 (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 15)
      - Insurance correspondence, 1934-1939; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-02, Folder 16-19)
      - Insurance correspondence, 1940-1945; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 1-2)
      - J miscellaneous, 1940; 1951 (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 3)
      - Jansen, Inc., 1937-1945; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 4-5)
      - Maison Jemont, 1936-1937 (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 6)
      - Jenkins House, 1937-1945; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 7-9)
      - K miscellaneous, 1938-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 9)
      - Kende Galleries, Inc., Gimbel Brothers, 1945-1946 (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 10)
      - Kingsley House, 1941; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 11)
      - Charles F. Krug Jr., 1937-1942; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 12-15)
      - L miscellaneous, 1939-1940; 1944 (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 16)
      - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1933-1954; (4 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 17-20)
      - Leon Lacroix, 1938-1950; (2 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 21-22)
      - Levi: Correspondence with/re: Gaston Levi, art restorer, 1939-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-03, Folder 23)
      - M miscellaneous, 1938-1952 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 1)
      - Rayner McConnal, 1938-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 2)
      - Lady Mendl purchases, 1949-1950 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 3)
      - Mensing auction Amsterdam, 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 4)
      - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1940-1949 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 5)
      - N. Mitchell, 1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 6)
      - Mystic Art Association, Connecticut, 1938 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 7)
      - N miscellaneous, 1938-1941 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 8)
      - New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 9)
      - Parish-Watson and Co., 1941 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 10)
      - Parke-Bernet, 1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 11)
      - Frank Partridge and Sons, 1938-1972 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 12)
      - Penson and Co., 1938-1942; (3 folders) (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 13-15)
      - Petit, Marcel and Gilbert, 1939-1940 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 16)
      - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1940-1948 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 17)
      - Pitt and Scott, 1938-1939 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 18)
      - Rosenberg and Steibel, 1951-1953 (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 19)
      - H. L. Rowland, 1939; undated (Box 1986.IA.48-04, Folder 20)